We have done our scan and we have also run the algorithm that makes it watertight.
And then after what we want to do is that we want to cut and manipulate the mesh,
take out the parts that we don't want, and this we can do it in Rhino.
If you want to just smooth out your model only like in the places that it is rough,
I recommend that you do use this Sculptris program because it's like a brush and you can actually
import here OBJ. You can take one here. So import Lara and do not resize in a new scene.
It will be a little bit heavy because this program normally is working with very simple
very simple things. But the good thing is that here you have this brush so it can smooth.
You can flatten.
No? So you can make it very soft. You can see the strength that you want.
So here, but here we want to inflate a little bit so we can inflate. But you don't want to inflate so
that this goes one into the other like that. This is bed. This is a bed mesh. It's better if it's
like more bumpy and it's not like that because this means that the two meshes are one side the other
and this will give you problems if you want to directly 3D print your program. So in this case
you would do like something like smoothen it out like this. So you can actually smooth out the
places that you want and you can make it like perfect with this in the places that if your
scan is quite good. This one for example, we didn't even run the algorithm to take out these small
pieces because inside the scannec you can choose like delete pieces that are smaller than x number.
So it would have deleted that. So anyway, then after you export it sstl or you save it and this
would be only for smoothening out in the beginning the mesh. Then after, okay, we go to rhino and
for going to rhino we need to import the mesh. So I import the, yes,
so import groups or is nothing actually, it doesn't matter. I import that. It will be heavy.
Okay, then I do zoom selected which is zs so that actually it zooms out to where I want.
Then here I see everything black because I right click and here it's a wireframe so basically
I want to see it's shaded. It will take a render. So here rendered, rendered, rendered with right
click on this or ghost it whatever. So here I have a mesh. Oh, it moved undo. I have a mesh.
The first thing is that I need to understand what scale this is. If it is smaller big. So I do
distance and I measure with the eye but having project on this thing on it is one of the snaps.
This doesn't take into account the third dimension. So it only will calculate from here to here in a
perpendicular way and it will not go like back in the third dimension. So if you measure here
from here to here you see in the perspective that this is horizontal but if you don't have
project sometimes it sees the third space and it is not straight. So you need to use project
if you want to only calculate two dimensions. So this is project I measure from here to here
down it says it's like one meter five one thousand five hundred eight five million. So the scale is
correct. It is the real scale and this if I click on it down I see that this is a mesh. So actually
I click here and it says Nana now it's a mesh. So if I want to see what kind of mesh this is
I will go here I will select that I will go here in this direction. So I will do show
so zoom naked zoom naked. So I select object with naked edges and down it will say the object
object doesn't have any naked meshes which means that it is watertight which means that there is
no like a hole because we did this before in sconect we closed it. So now this mesh I don't
like to manipulate meshes in Rhino but Rhino is not a program for manipulation of mesh.
So I will do mesh to nerbs which is actually merged to nerb which is actually
so it's saved saved. So I do mesh to nerbs.
It will say that you have too many faces you will run out of memory. Let's try.
And then it doesn't do anything. So yeah good. Yeah it will do something. If it doesn't if it
cannot if it's like too high resolution we will manipulate the mesh but it's better always to
convert it into poly surface. It's a different kind of geometry basically to work in Rhino.
But sometimes maybe in your computers you need to have like patience.
It will it may happen like it I think it will do it. It will finally convert it.
Also like the fact that we have the the texture here is not helping so much with the
yeah.
Actually it's part of the render.
And
the other program while it's doing that the other program that you can use is the mesh mixer.
So the mesh mixer also is like a sculpting program. You can see that you can import your
or you can do like the bunny. No and then here you can analyze for example its strength.
You can see where it is more like keen to break. You can analyze the
you can measure it inspected like orient it. You can edit
like not duplicate now but you can sculpt it so you know like you can do.
So that's very nice.
I mean this kind of model you cannot actually like you you would print this kind of stuff.
No you cannot do it with any other kind of technology like this. It's better for 3d printing
but yes you can play with the strength of volume here. You have different brushes that they
draw and they draw so it's like a little bit like sculptories but it's more for like meshes
and you have some primitives also that you can use. So it's free. This is free
and then you can have like the analysis. Okay this is not really responding.
So you can stamp it.
I don't know how I hear in this one. There are two there is a copy. Anyway this one you can play.
They are very nice like easy programs and then another one that you can use is the mesh lab
where the mesh lab actually is quite nice because it has these filters.
So the mesh lab here it has some filters so you can simplify the mesh.
So you can make like you can make a uniform mesh resampling so it's very annoying. So here
you can do... oh sorry it says here.
So here it makes like... it is a filter.
The fun thing is that I put very little polygons so it makes like a big polygon.
It remeshed like something that is not correct.
It's using different algorithms and libraries and then you can triangulate for example
because now the mesh is like more smooth but you can make like more bigger triangles.
You can like change it with filters. Anyway so this one I will kill it.
So it doesn't want to get to NERM and I will directly like manipulate it as a mesh and here
you can find all the commands that you can... oh you cannot see there. Can you see them there?
So you cannot see here that the thing is... oh yes you can see. So here are all the commands for a mesh.
And here you have like all the commands for solids or the command for surfaces.
Like surfaces 2D, cares, which are lines, dimension for measuring, transforming. So you can do everything
in Rhino from the top bar but you can also do everything from the sidebar with icons or you
can also write everything. So there are three ways to do the same thing. So in this case what I want
to do is that I want to make a box and I want to put this box here and this box needs to be like
bigger. And then I will... I did it with here with this icon but if you want you can also write box
for example and if you want you can go solid box. It's the same thing with three ways. So then after
I will move the box here and basically this is... if you see this one is... if you see down it says
it is an extrusion and this one is a mesh. So these two people are not friends. They cannot do anything
together. Like you cannot join them, you cannot cut them, you cannot... because they are different
families. One is one kind of type of geometry and the other is one other kind of type of geometry.
So basically meshes can be manipulated with meshes, solids with solids, surfaces with surfaces and all
the families all... all together. You cannot do anything between a solid and a mesh. So what you
need to do is that to do this box convert it into a mesh. So I will mesh it and then it asks me how
many polygons you want. I do it default. So basically I convert the geometry of the solids
to... of the extrusion to the geometry of a mesh and I could have done the same for the mesh
with this command that I showed you before which is mesh to nerves but it's too many polygons so
basically I will not. So now here if I click I have two things one extrusion and one mesh.
One inside the other at the same spot. So I choose the extrusion and I delete it. So now this one is
a mesh and this one is a mesh. So let's see... so now I will save that first always try to save.
Okay and then now what I will try to do is that I will try to make a Boolean operation.
Boolean operations are the operations that you have two objects A and B and then you can do Boolean
union. So you can do one object the object C or you can do a Boolean split. So you have the A
without this part the B without this part and the small object which is the intersection of the two
as a C or you can make the difference of them. So you say A minus B so it's only this one. So there
are different operations as we call Boolean operations and here as you can see you have
Boolean difference, Boolean split, Boolean union. In general personally I prefer to do
Boolean split. So I have everything that I had in the beginning but split and then I delete what I have
but you can try all of them. So in this case I want to do a Boolean split but for mesh
I need to choose mesh Boolean split which is there. It's only for the meshes.
So what do I want to split? I want to split Jenny with the box. Enter. So now it will
calculate for a moment down you can see mesh Boolean split in progress and hopefully it will split it.
So you have been able to convert Jenny into NERBs you don't need to do the mesh box you can just do
boxes. Yes and best Boolean split with the normal command. Yeah so it seems that it did it because
now it's not calculating anymore so let's see Jenny. So Jenny is without the base that's cool.
The other thing is that so now we can delete that. The cool thing with the Boolean which is a
difference between trim because you can also cut trim it's the command trim. The cool thing with the
Boolean is that it will make it solid so it will close this. You will have a surface that is closed
which means that your model is still watertight. If you did a trim you would be cutting but then
it will be open and you would have no surface under you. You want me to do a one trim so that you
can see the difference? Yes it stays hollow so you will only see like as if you had the
peter miss no the one surface of this body but inside there was nothing and this is not appropriate
for manipulation c3d printing or anything and basically there are commands that you can do
like the command the cap which puts like caps on the open objects but this is only for objects that
they are flat. If it's like a curved surface that you can you need to close cap will not work.
Now I will do the same here and here maybe because I don't want this
I don't want this hand for example.
So yes so let's do this zoom selected enter so I can a little bit rotate her
so that it she's straight or like
like there and then I can make a box here but then you see I cannot see the third dimension I go
and I design here so you can have like a this one I design a box in this side for one dimension so
and then in this screen front screen for the other dimension basically
it's mandatory that the box it is bigger goes out from the thing from the mesh
because the Boolean is easier calculated so okay I do that
and then I will mesh them okay and then I will actually select
extrusions and delete the extrusions because in Rhino I can select families of objects I can
select meshes and it will select everything or I can select points and then it will say
there are no points there are no points in this thing okay anyway and then I will mesh
Boolean split again I want to split this because it asks always Rhino will ask you what do you
want to do and you have to read that no you have to read it says select meshes all porous surfaces
to split and then press enter enter with what do you want to split it with this
so then I will wait again and then finally here I have this so I can delete that and then I will
do the same with I want to split this with that enter so now that it's a little bit more cut
okay I will save it
and then I will try again to do it mesh to nerves or maybe no it doesn't matter no no
so it's okay so if I want now to put this model in
a slicer I will file export selected I select what I want to do export and I always do export
selected just don't ask why just do it like that because there are many problems if you just export
because there are other things in the scene and then it's like a big mess for the 3d printer and
just always export selected and I select what you want to export and then I can export it as obg
so this is Jenny cut
and here you just leave it as it is don't
uh yeah you can export it as nerves also in any case now
yeah we we are going to do it as object so now I go to slicer for fusion 360
and um basically
yeah it would be nice for example this model to open it in sculptures and see also smooth it out
like whatever like it has bumps or like a little bit with a tush like to touch it because
we from the scar need to come sound like more bumpy so Jenny no water tight
Jenny cut open and then here what will happen is that
if you want to do all the body of Jenny we should split it and have two files because the laser
cutter is one meter by 600 so you cannot do higher than one meter so basically when you want to
do your money team you have to make a box that is one meter exactly put the part that you want to
do inside and cut the rest because the laser cutter is one meter and if you want to do the
two parts then you have to split them and do them separately and then join them
when you assemble it in this laser cutter
yeah so I use the OBG but if you can import the STL in Rhino maybe it doesn't have the texture so
maybe it's lighter but tribal that's not so for sure the scant object will be more
heavy than the make human body you know because the scant object became out from the
point cloud that was triangulated and then there was an algorithm that ran and closed the holes and
you don't know if it closed them correctly so
can you do it now yeah maybe
the way I will say
so if we want to do Jenny the correct size we would cut her head
so in order to cut her head it's better if we cut it not like straight no if we cut it for example
like
like this no
no this will be very problematic is a good example actually to see
so if I want to cut her head like that or maybe a little bit like
I rotate it and I move it a little bit like that yeah so this one I will extrude it
like this and then I will extrude the surface like that
oh yeah and then I will just mash it okay delete the extrusion the poly surface
and then mesh boolean split this one with this one
and
then
yes and then you see here is a little bit not good so I need to continue cleaning but
I will go to the front view and I will make a line from here and it will be I will make a line
here a curve from here polyline from here and it will be 1000 which is one meter wow
so now you need to tell us your height before I cut your head
and
where is Jenny you need to tell us your height before I cut
yes
like from here
to here
155 155 0
ah no I didn't do correctly sorry I will do it again so I make a polyline from here
to here and I will write 155 0 enter click and done okay so I don't see the polyline the reason I
don't see the polyline is because I have it in rendered and lines cannot be rendered if I have
it in wireframe I can see it so shade it I can see it ghosted I can see it but rendered lines
cannot be rendered anyway so this one is your height so basically I will scale you a little bit
scale
and I will put like from here to here and here okay so I made a line in the correct size
and then I grabbed it and I scale it with a reference of the line so now I can delete that
and now I can make this line which will be from here
to here one meter which is the size of the laser cutter okay
and then
and then actually I need to make a box which will be this box and for the third dimension I just go
to perspective and I do like that maybe I just don't need to do like exactly one meter because it's
exactly one meter the laser cutter so it's good like to leave some margin so I can move this
front I can move this move this by 50 millimeters so it's like I have like some space and then I
will match the box and then
oh yeah if you want to do the whole body then you would have to separate it only
and you put the slicer but then you will assemble it they will be like laser cutting
half and laser cutting the other half and then you have to try to find a way to join them
which is more complicated and anyway so this is the mesh
and then here I delete the extrusion so don't worry if you don't get it for the first time
because we will do it so many times that you will learn it and I think that I'm recording the session
so I will send it to you tonight and so mesh boolean split what I want to split this with what I want
to split it with that and then I also take that so actually I have to still clean here
and in order to be able to so here you see that there is an error
this is bad because this will come out in the slicer so basically
I will tell you how to do it so here it would be good to cut this
so in order to cut this I will go to the right view yes and now I will cut this so
so
extrude no no an extrude but it's a it's extruding in a direction that I don't want
so what I will do is that I will say here direction
and I will tell that the direction is from here and then to there
so here sorry so here the problem is that this one is very small in the backside here
it doesn't go a little bit like out and it will fail so I need to move it a little bit
and then I will have to extrude this surface because every time I want to extrude something
it's like selecting what kind of geometry I have and then I will do a mesh again
and then I will Boolean split this one no mesh Boolean split this one with this one
yeah so let's take this out and now here
here
well it's not perfect so I will do like
yeah I will do another line no no it's okay and it's also okay so it left so because my
my volume that I the box that I made was not so big it left this and this is bad
so basically I will I will have to do it again you know like make a big no because
they you see that you see here redo delete redo redo oh no redo redo these ones they are together
it's one thing if I want to split them I would do like I would try and group
no it's better it's better actually to make this box bigger scale 1d in one dimension
so basically from here to here and make it bigger and now I will mesh Boolean split
this one with I don't know but sorry guys it's here I it's together again edit redo extrude surface
redo mesh redo delete the thing and now scale only in one dimension
because I only want to scale in this dimension from here to here and there and then mesh Boolean
split this one with this one
so it doesn't you see it doesn't do it it has an error it makes like so what happens is that here
I basically am too much down and I need to put this a little bit more up
so let's see better
here in the right view what is happening so okay this should be fine
I actually can move it until here yeah so mesh Boolean split mesh Boolean split
this one with this one
okay so let's see
okay so next time the hair should be tighter
no it's it's okay anyway now I will file export selected
and Jenny more cut SNBG
okay so here you see it says export mesh texture coordinates we don't want the texture
so I just take this out
and now we can go back to here so
so here we have Jenny and the thing is that when you open that
program first of all you see that it's the both it's like it put it like horizontal this is like
you see it's put it like in the other direction this you choose it when you open the software
but I chose like the the Y like I chose like the the long side of this object is the Y so it
opened it like down anyway so basically we need to go here and say that we are we were working in
millimeters and then we need to go here and put that we want this in this original size
because it automatically open and have it to escape
so now we can see that this is the height actually it says width because it's horizontal
so that's perfect then the next thing we need to do is that we need to press this setting thing
manufacturing settings and it is very important because we need to define what is the size of
the material that we're going to use so what is the size of the boards the card on the so here
down when you click here up in the settings then if you go down here you can put that you work
millimeters and you can put that the size of the cardboard is one meter which is one thousand
by six hundred and the thickness of the board is four so basically the size of the laser cutter
is the size of the boards that we are going to buy which is one meter by six hundred and the
thickness of the boards that we are going to buy will be four for example so what will happen here
and now it's this is okay so this is the custom you have to go here and select the custom that you
put down and here you can choose the construction techniques so here you have the stacked slices
for example so here it will make all the stacked slices and then you can get the assembly plans
and it will visualize how you need to assemble it you see
well this one is super easy but you see that it needs like
all these boards and it's not good so we will not do that and then you have the interlocked slices
so you see here that is all red why
why is it all red
is it empty
basically the problem is that when it's red it's like it means that it doesn't you cannot make it
and the reason here is because this genie is one meter fifty and my boards are one meter so it doesn't fit
you know so
I could do the genie one meter here but this is like a scaled version
no I can scale it there but I don't want to scale it there because it means that everything that
I had calculated before is wrong so basically I if I scale it it's very good in dry land
when you are in the last step of the fabrication that like one moment before you go to laser cut
it's better not to scale in general like if you design it and you scale it when you're designing
you know but if it doesn't fit for last week so here I will make it like even smaller
so this is a mignon like a small genie
so here you can actually select
there's still doesn't fit because it puts it in this direction so
yeah it puts it in the 600 because it's a little bit problematic the software
because it will as I imported it horizontal and it wants to do horizontal so it cannot understand
that it can rotate it in the program but what I could do is that I could go here and I can put
that this is 600 and this is 1000 you see
okay so now we we can put like more or less if we want here and then we can also
so we can also change the slice direction if you want to make it like
change the degree here
and you can play with the direction of the slices
in the different axis
so
for some reason modify form and you can also I mean if you're using this technique
here you get the assembly steps so
so
you can choose plastic play would only for visualization so what happens here I want
to tell you something very very important and I finish
this one you see that it has two slots one here and one here but this one is
small so it's okay doesn't matter this one enters nicely this one enters nicely
this one enters okay this one enters but this one that has this hole here
I mean actually it cannot enter it's wrong the program basically has a bug that is not
perfect the program so sometimes it's if you have like something that is up and down it makes
like two slots but actually in reality you cannot put it because you would need you would need to
have like one continuous slot for passing it from down all up so just take care that this
if this thing happens because if this happens this happens we just open it in Rhino
and we delete that path you know like because here it cannot enter in the three slots it's if
I mean it will be like one big piece if it's if it's three if it is three pieces it enters
but if it is one big piece sometimes the program thinks that you can put it like that but it you
cannot so just beware of these two slots thing when it happens I mean here I don't know if it's
only a small piece or big but sometimes and if it is if it has problems so it's small piece
if it has problems so this one yeah you can put it you can see it read like as we did before
that's it
here in the account so you can choose by distance and you put every the distance or you can just
and say okay I want 10 in this direction and two in this direction you see
and then you can also do the radial slices which is so
but it's a little bit difficult but it's nice one time I did ah and you can also
choose this size of this hole here modify form you can make it hollow you see
so but you don't want to make this hollow because it will be very difficult to assemble
but if you were doing stacks stacked slices and you want to put like a light inside
then you would make it hollow
and then you get the plants and then you you get one layer in red that is the engraving
layer for the laser cutter and one layer that is the blue one that is for cutting and then you
define the power and the speed in the laser cutter for engraving and the power and the
speed for laser cutting I think that's it